#### Contact

tonyjbailey@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ tonybaileyinnovation (LinkedIn)

## Top Skills

Nursing Healthcare Management Hospitals

## Certifications

Healthcare Innovation and Entrepreneurship

#### Honors-Awards

Verizon Powerful Answers Award Nurse of the Year- Professional Support

Nurse of the Year- Honorable Mention

# Tony Bailey, MBA, BSN, RN

Clinical Innovation Consultant at Sparrow Specialty Hospital East Lansing, Michigan

## Summary

Healthcare innovation motivates me as the opportunities are endless. Bachelor's prepared Registered Nurse with MBA and 20 years of clinical nursing experience in the acute care setting. Skilled leader with 5 years of leadership experience as a Healthcare Manager, Administrative Supervisor, and Risk Manager. Proven success in leading highly effective teams and creating collaborative work environments. Outstanding communication, excellent organization, flexibility, and ability to work in dynamic environments. Proactively identifies customer needs and develops meaningful ways to assist with solutions.

Strengths include patient safety, patient satisfaction, extensive clinical knowledge, process improvement, project management, and medical device innovation.

Certified in Healthcare Innovation and Entrepreneurship.

Trained in TeamSTEPPS and Six Sigma Yellow Belt.

# Experience

Sparrow Specialty Hospital 3 years 4 months Clinical Innovation Consultant November 2019 - Present (9 months)

Lansing, Michiggan

## RN

April 2017 - Present (3 years 4 months)

Lansing, Michigan Area

Sparrow Health System Interim Administrative Supervisor

#### July 2019 - Present (1 year 1 month)

Lansing, Michigan Area

## Sparrow Health System

5 years 6 months

#### FastCare Manager

August 2016 - April 2017 (9 months)

DeWitt, Michigan

Operational responsibilities for four FastCare clinics in the Mid-Michigan region including: strategic planning, marketing, annual budgeting, and business development.

### FastCare Manager

May 2016 - April 2017 (1 year)

Lansing, Michigan Area

Operational responsibilities for four FastCare clinics in the Mid-Michigan region including: strategic planning, marketing, annual budgeting, and business development.

#### FastCare Manager

May 2016 - April 2017 (1 year)

Okemos, Michigan Area

Operational responsibilities for four FastCare clinics in the Mid-Michigan region including: strategic planning, marketing, annual budgeting, and business development.

#### Risk Manager

February 2015 - May 2016 (1 year 4 months)

- Manage and analyze Risk Management data, conducting risk assessments on clinical practice and care design processes
- Assisted in the development and successful implementation of an online occurrence reporting system with 6,000 submissions per year
- Provide support, education, and training to new associates within the health system on occurrence reporting and risk identification process
- Oversee requests for real-time patient service recovery, including coordinating with Patient Experience department and hospital employees to increase patient satisfaction
- Develop and monitor Risk Management strategies and action plans to minimize the risk of injury to patients, visitors, and staff
- Collaborate with the Legal, Finance, and other appropriate internal departments regarding Risk Management matters

- Work in conjunction with the Quality Services, Privacy, and Performance Improvement in the design and implementation of policies and procedures related to loss prevention, patient safety, risk mitigation and patient rights
- Identifies and reduces areas with high malpractice potential; develops and administers comprehensive quality assurance program and investigates and follows-up all incidents reported
- Serve as a resource to physicians and hospital staff in clarifying and resolving risk management issues

## Administrative Nursing Supervisor November 2011 - January 2015 (3 years 3 months)

- Supervise the work of charge nurses and assistant department managers
- Oversee and manage a number of clinical and support staff in patient care activities while maintaining a high level of staff morale and professionalism
- Identified pertinent feedback from floor charge nurses and incorporated it into an improved new process for the nightly charge nurse bed meeting
- Developed and implemented an innovative noise reduction process to improve patient satisfaction
- Served as chairman on the Quiet at Night committee
- Developed and implemented a Strategic Investment in Charge
   Nurse Program for improved understanding of throughput process and interdepartmental patient flow processes
- Respond to all emergency situations

## Sparrow Health System Med-Surg, Intermediate, ER, IVSD, Float 2000 - 2011 (11 years)

- Medical Oncology / Medical Specialties: Oncology and hematology patients, hemodialysis, CAPD patients, geriatric patients and patients with a chronic medical diagnosis such as diabetes, pancreatitis, electrolyte imbalances or congestive heart failure
- Surgical Specialties: General surgery patients, including vascular, thoracic,
   GI/GU and ENT surgeries.
- Orthopedics: Ortho surgeries for laminectomies, total hips and knees, trauma, and major fractures.
- Neuro Step-down Unit: CVA, TIA, anterior cervical fusion surgeries, trauma, major back surgeries
- Cardiac Progressive Care Unit: Pre/post cardiac cath and intervention, pre/post open heart, arrhythmia, arterial lines and some vasoactive drips

- Medical Intermediate Care: Respiratory illnesses (such as COPD, asthma, pneumonia, respiratory failure) and medical illnesses (such as diabetes, sepsis, cellulitis), cardiac illnesses (such as CHF, PE, DVTs), vents.
- Cardiac Cath Lab Recovery: Cardiac procedures, pacemakers, implantable cardioverter defibrillator, ablations, stents, pacing, pulling arterial sheaths, cardiac medication changes
- Emergency Department: Level 1 Trauma Center
- Pediatric Emergency Department
- Pediatric
- IV Specialty Department: Expert in intravascular access >95% success rate, PICC line care, tunneled catheters
- Endoscopy Unit: Colonoscopies, EGD, bronchoscopies
- Urgent Care
- Post-anesthesia Care Unit
- Observation/Overflow Units
- Adult Psychiatric
- Geriatric Psychiatry
- Nurse of the Year 2011, Professional Support Sparrow Hospital
- Nurse of the Year 2005, Honorable Mention Sparrow Hospital
- Routinely utilized in the charge nurse role
- Responsible for training new associates
- Represented multiple departments in contract negotiations
- Influential ideas used in developing overflow units
- Demonstrated ability to forge, lead, and motivate outstanding healthcare teams that provide top-quality patient care

Cottage Health System ER Nurse 2008 - 2009 (1 year)

McLaren Greater Lansing ER Nurse 2004 - 2005 (1 year)

# Education

Michigan State University
Bachelor's degree, Registered Nursing/Registered Nurse

Columbia Southern University

Master of Business Administration (MBA), Health/Health Care Administration/ Management · (2012 - 2014)